Our video presentation will be entitled
Algorithmic
Translation versus Human Imagination
and Electronic Storytelling.
This is from Doctor Gloria Wilson. Ian.
So yeah.
Within the everyone.
And let me also welcome everyone to this
and yellow
unsupervised and conference.
It's my pleasure to present
this paper
that I want to believe will help us
have maybe some interactive moments
or maybe a time of discovering
a few things.
Maybe we have a kind of at this
point for all of us.
The the title of this presentation
is Algorithms
translations versus Human Imagination
in Electronic Storytelling.
I want to talk about how algorithms
and human imagination
work together in electronics to tourism.
As with a focus on English
and French translation in Nigerian games
and films.
The background to
this work is about
is on storytelling storytelling
that has with games, films
and interactive media.
It also has to do with tools that now
handle translation, dialog and subtitles.
We have
like an AI
subtitles for running films on Netflix
and all that,
and then also some real time
English
as frank localization for mobile games.
We know that we are in an era
where it came in
Lagos can be played in that car
the next week.
A translation means possible.
But Pete, a loan is not enough.
We have as a first problem
we are going to look at it
between efficiency that is a fast, cheap,
multilingual, rich and meaning
it has to do with a cultural tone
and context.
For example, here I will translate his
my guide to mean My God.
But humans know better
because it's about relationship,
it's about emotions and all that.
So the human who said semaphore then same
put them on, put all the water, same
god depending on the context.
So here the problem is simple
algorithms give us kill
when they offer me.
Then once a little friend translation
can break it up
or change the relationship.
So how do we relate or balance?
Because
the objectives
of this work will be changed, mean
the role of algorithms in translation
for games and film, and also to examine
the role of human imaginaries
in adapting to risk.
And also number three
will propose a hybrid model
for Nigerian electronic storytelling.
I have to first look at what does well,
then what humans do well
and then how to combine them.
Because in the conceptual framework
we look at algorithms,
which is called data automation,
and then how repetition and scales
are handled,
then imaginaries, human creativity,
culture, emotion, how harmony is handled,
and then the obedience as a section
that is a hybrid story.
So imaginaries they will now enter
into investment section.
We think of algorithms
as the engine and imaginaries.
As a driver
you need both to reach the destination.
Algorithms and storytelling.
What are the rhythms? Do well
in speed, yes, because they can
translate 1000 words in hours, not weeks.
The scale English, French
for multiple countries as well.
You know they can translate
into the different you know, you know,
varieties of friend in Canada,
in Paris, in Senegal, in Africa.
The cartoons give that within few hours.
And then there is consistency.
Sentences
across the whole came from the same times.
It's well,
also even though there's consistency,
they could take steps
and they can also be substance in
AI localizes a mobile game
from French
to English to French for Cameroon,
and then simultaneously.
This is a big win.
Without AI, a small Nigerians to a studio
could never afford to translate
into French
for all of Francophone Africa.
So what do the human imaginaries do when
in contact cultural contexts?
They understand human.
They understand tool
and relationships in emotion.
They adapt, done to feel natural.
Then in the that they decide what to keep,
what to change, or what you explain.
You know in translation.
We know that when you are doing
translations like entering into a theater,
that's how you have
a different technical production,
have the different techniques we have.
We have a problem,
we have card, we have all the other ones.
Station modulation.
The rest is like entering into a theater.
You, you when you do a surgery, you remove
what is normal
then and put back what is in the state
of that level of stitching.
In top is where we have
whatever is in there in translation.
So for example, we have
if you are changing from let's go to you
say on user that or you say Ali,
this will depend on if the characters
are friends or associates.
So he must know that French in Abuja
is not the same as French in Paris.
And humans decide
what sounds real to her audience.
That's the thing.
So we have to convert your analysis
in terms of dimension.
We have algorithms that listen
and the imagination
for speak in the area of dimension.
You see, it's very fast in algorithmic
translation, and it's slower
in human imagination for scalability,
in algorithmic translation,
it is an easily scalable
to multiple languages, but limited in
human
imagination, is limited by human hours.
In the cultural context, it is, you know,
what comes to algorithmic translation.
It is weak with idioms and tools.
The that of the human imagination
is strong emotions and all that.
The when it comes to cost for the trust,
the ordinary translation,
it is lower and it is after sector,
it is low.
And then for human it is higher
because you need a lot of hearts.
You need to get,
you know, a lot of things come into play.
So it's higher in terms, of course,
when it comes to creativity
for algorithmic translation,
it is pattern based.
And then when it comes to human
validation, it is original
and adapted here.
So what we mean here
is that the table adoption shows the trade
of algorithms win or speed across
humans win our culture credibility.
But at the end of the day,
we know we need both.
So there's a little case here.
Translation in Nigerian games
of in the case for Nigeria mobile games
in AI English to French.
Your friend from France
when the second countries
we say that means the level of passport
nivel and superior for natural to win
the results.
It is whether it is natural languages
in case study two no linguist
or stream as such past French subtitles
in 48 hours for human.
For example, he said he's my guy.
You the thing that
comes to the seven put
because it is something
that personal, it's
personally to you to cut your friendship.
And then the result is this fast
distribution and the meaning is spread.
It is present in the distribution.
It goes faster because meaning is added
and it is something that is closer to
our home study.
So the key takeaway here is an organism's
made natural.
So it's tribal imaginaries.
Make them connect.
In Nigeria we create in English
to reach the Caribbean when we need French
AI gives us speed that give us the right
French for our audience.
The key finding here is in hybrid models,
the hybrid models works best.
Algorithm rules, translation
consistency and fast
trust afford imaginary rules.
You have the meeting cultural
and attention to the control.
And then we made it to the YouTube
auto captions in English humanity
to adapt French subtitles for West African
you know audience.
Listen.
We see on the screen, they are immediately
done at times the the context,
the content may not actually reflect the
the the the real meaning.
So the best workflow is AI first, human
second.
Let the machine to 80% of the work,
then letting
humans make it 100% right in
for the parts
you were scared hired to us
for quality for researchers
study how AI handles English, French
in African context for policies.
Invest in training
for AI plus human transition tribes.
If you want Nigerian stories to go global,
we need to fund both the tech
and the people who make it work for us.
In conclusion, I will say
algorithms provide rich and efficiency
imaginaries provide
meaning and cultural connection.
The future of Nigerian electronic sewing
telling is hybrid English
and French together, concurrent stories
across Africa and beyond.
To conclude, you do not have to choose
between AI and humans.
No, not at all.
We don't need to make that choice.
What you have to know
is that the future is both.
It is both AI and humans.
That's how Nigerian stories will travel.
And see if you like us.
And I want to say
thank you very much for your attention.
I want to believe that this will help us
explore more into the world
of AI and human translation.
Thank you very much.